hey folks read here it has been an
incredibly interesting week
last Wednesday Dave Rubin invited me to
join him onstage in Bellevue Washington
for a comedy in questions event which
was quite extraordinary the following
night I attended the Jordan Peterson
lecture in Seattle in preparation for
the debates last weekend in Vancouver
between Jordan Peterson and Sam Harris
which I had the privilege of moderating
there's definitely something going on
all of the audiences in these various
venues were utterly enthusiastic and
they appeared to be enthusiastic about
the breakdown of the tired sense-making
apparatus that we've all been stuck with
for so long and its replacement by
something new interesting and
unpredictable if you haven't been to one
of these live events I highly recommend
it I think you will discover something
very exciting as a foot if you can't get
to one of these live events and maybe
even if you can I would recommend
looking into the Rubin report with Eric
Weinstein ben shapiro and jordan
peterson and one prior to that with
jordan peterson and eric weinstein both
of those discussions are of quite a new
sort I think we're really breaking new
ground and lots of positions that have
previously been thought to be
unreconciled both are beginning to
converge on some kind of new
reasonableness
it's very hopeful now I want to say a
few words about the debates in Vancouver
I chose at the beginning of those
evenings to ask the audience not to
livestream or record the events and it
appears that nobody did on the basis
that no video has emerged so thank you
for listening to me and taking that
request seriously I do have some concern
now that the videos that were taken
officially of those events are not going
to emerge for quite some time and that
creates a problem let me say a few words
about why I made the request to begin
with my thought having seen several of
these events of different kinds now is
that there's a palpable difference
between those events that are
immediately brought to the Internet and
events in which the room in which the
event takes place is isolated from the
internet for some period of time I
wasn't sure exactly why the difference
existed my thought was that perhaps
participants are a little bit more
relaxed about what they say in the
context of a room that is not
immediately being broadcast to the
outside world in the aftermath of the
vancouver debates i've changed my mind a
little bit about why the difference
exists my feeling now is that there is a
necessity for the room to be able to
decide what it saw before the internet
weighs in and when an event is broadcast
it when it is streamed or when it is
immediately released there's a tendency
for the internet reaction to overwhelm
the reaction of the room and it can
actually override it
so I do think it's a good idea for
events especially ones that are likely
to change the nature of the dialogue
like a debate between sam harris and
jordan peterson where progress is made
and things are different at the end of
the evening than they were before it's
very important for those events I think
to be insulated from the internet for
long enough for the room to come to a
conclusion about what it saw before it
gets overwhelmed by the outside
I don't think however that it's healthy
to have a very long delay in such a case
I'm particularly concerned that jordan
peterson and sam harris are going to
meet again very soon in dublin and in
london and they will of course be
meeting from the position that they
arrived at at the end of their vancouver
meeting but their audience is now
divided there are those people who were
in vancouver and are up-to-date on the
change in their understanding of each
other and then there's the majority of
the audience which wasn't in vancouver
and hasn't been able to grapple with the
change in both men's positions i think
that poses a danger that it's a little
bit hard to describe but it is possible
that the audience failing to update its
model of where the two positions that
these men hold are at the moment
will cause them to regress and that the
progress that they made which I think
was very substantial may also be a
little bit fragile so we're at mine to
decide I would have those tapes released
so that the internet could view them and
come to understand them before Jordan
and Sam meet in Dublin and in London I
don't think that's going to happen and
so I feel I owe an apology to the
audience for making the request I did
had I known that it might be a very long
time before the tapes were going to
emerge I would not have made that
request so I would also ask something of
the audience which is give Sam and
Jordan room to let you know in their own
way the ways in which their perspectives
have been modified I saw today on reddit
that somebody had posted a quote from
Sam from I don't know how long ago but
it was clearly a very harsh judgment of
Jordan Peterson's perspective and I know
it does not fit with his current
understanding it's one example of the
kind of of tension that could pull one
or both of these people backwards so
please resist the urge to pull them and
I hope that they will find a way to
bring their London and Dublin audiences
up to speed as quickly as possible those
events in London and Dublin are going to
be quite different than the Vancouver
events for one thing they won't be
moderated they will be joined by Douglas
Murray who is a wonderful human being in
his own right I met him several weeks
ago and I think they are sure to have a
fascinating discussion but it will not
be a discussion in which there is
somebody whose purpose is to help them
not talk past each other in any case I
do hope that the momentum that has taken
over this movement if that's what it is
continues and that we will find a way to
continue to level up so we can keep
discovering greater nuance that will
allow us to process the reality that we
find ourselves in with ever
greater accuracy thanks very much and I
look forward to meeting many of you in
the future